ShinY
深影
本字幕由 ShinY 深影字幕组原创翻译制作
深影字幕组论坛地址http://shinybbs.vip
■
你是我的伊丽莎白
You're my Elizabeth...
前情提要
没人能戏弄你
and no one else is to play with you.
全国的天主教徒都在支持您
You have the backing of every single Catholic in this country.
ShinY
深影
我们为何非要资助一场
I question why we are asked to fund
■
ShinY
深影
据说是必胜的战争
a war we were told was won.
之前确实胜利在望
Because it was!
可你觉得半夜偷偷送走一个女孩
Or do you believe stealing a girl away in the middle of the night
请求法国援助 是胜者所为吗
and pleading for French assistance the act of winners?
都是为我安排的吗
All this for me?
我家夫人还在担心把女儿
My wife questions whether you and Catherine
交给你和凯瑟琳照顾是好是坏
are the best guardians for Jane,
ShinY
深影
将来能让她跟国王成婚吗
matching her with the king in the future.
听着 该让我来主持...
Listen! I am meant to conduct...
够了
Enough!
你不是来此治国
You are in this room not to rule
而是向朝臣学习治国之道 尤其是我
but to learn from those that do, from me.
你做了什么不重要
What you've done does not matter.
ShinY
深影
你还是担心别人觉得
It's what people think you have done
ShinY
深影
你做了什么吧
that is all that matters now.
明人不做暗事
切森特庄园
你手好凉
Your hands are cold.
伤心难过的事...
All those things that upset you...
就都留在切尔西庄园吧
just leave them behind at Chelsea.
您的身子要紧
You'll make yourself unwell.
菜不合您胃口吗 公主
Is it not to your liking, Princess?
她可能是乏了
Perhaps she's tired.
我还没走呢
She is present.
请殿下恕罪
Forgive us.
我姐姐常提起殿下
My sister so oft talks of Your Grace.
我和安东尼爵士
Sir Anthony and I'd likely feel
都和她一样喜爱您
quite as much affection for you as she.
再怎么喜爱也不会像这般亲近吧
Affection must not slip into overfamiliarity, though.
我知道您觉得我无礼 公主殿下
I know you find me rude, Princess.
每次我都深感抱歉
I do apologize for it every time.
可我不想有意同您拉近关系
But overfamiliarity is a charge I will not take.
先王 也就是您父王 在弥留之际
I held your father, the king's, hand
是我握着先王的手
as he lay dying.
就算不跟公主您沾亲带故
So if not you, your kin,
我也熟悉您的亲人
I am familiar with.
那您今天有看到我的信件吗 安东尼爵士
Are you familiar with any of my letters today, Sir Anthony?
公主殿下
Princess.
尚未收到您的信件
No letters have come for you.
我说过如果有会告诉您的
I have told you I would tell you if they did.
但现在没有
No word.
想必您是在等您继母
I assume it is your stepmother, Catherine,
凯瑟琳的来信
you're so anxious to hear from.
可是到现在也没见她来信
Strange she has not written once in all this time.
她怀有身孕 不便通信
She's unwell due to her pregnancy.
是吗
Is she?
我听说可不是这样
That's not what I heard.
我知道自己总说您是急性子 可现在
I know I chide you for not keeping patience, but Lord,
我那妹夫分明是派来考验你我二人的
my sister's husband was sent to test mine as much as yours.
我的月事还没来 凯特
I'm late, Kat.
来这里之后 月经从未来潮
I have not bled since we arrived here.
你也知道
You know this.
我知道您的月事不规律
Yes, you've never been regular.
非要我把话说明吗
Please don't make me say it.
你肯定知道我的意思
You know. Surely you know.
本以为您对他只是一时欢喜
I imagined you'd taken a silly fancy to him.
可没想到...
But this...
何时的事
When?
不知...
I could not...
您多次与他同床吗
More than once you lay with him?
我以为自己很了解您 伊丽莎白
I thought I knew you, Elizabeth.
要找人帮我看看吗
Should we fetch a woman?
你不会告诉你妹妹吧
You wouldn't tell your sister, would you?
就算你觉得她可信
Even if you think she could be trusted,
我也不希望她知道
I couldn't bear her knowing.
真要找人帮我看看
I couldn't bear anyone knowing,
这事不就暴露了吗
if we... We fetch a woman.
您对这种事有多少了解
How knowledgeable you are in these matters.
我知道纸包不住火
I know they can be found.
- 大家都知道能... - 住嘴
- Everyone knows they can... - Quiet!
要是传出去
If word gets out,
你我都要人头落地
then we will both lose our heads.
您的月事经常晚来 我们可以坐视不管
You're often late. There is no need to act yet.
等到时候您还没来月事
If in time you still don't bleed,
我再去找人
I will find someone.
但现在要讳而不言
But for now, tell no one.
凯瑟琳太后知道吗
Does our Lady Catherine know?
真是自寻烦恼
What pain you have caused.
自取其辱
And shame you have brought.
深影原创译制
翻译 杨梅
翻译 Albert
翻译 黑猫
翻译 青鸟
翻译 小明
校对 Noel
压制 JoshuaX
特效 Noel
《成则为王》
第四集 开诚布公
请别这样
Please. No.
滚开
Fuck off.
我早就想这么干了
I've always wanted to do that.
宽恕要多少钱呢 神父
How much for forgiveness, Father?
卑鄙无耻的天主教徒
Filthy fucking Catholics.
对旧教的信奉将不复存在
As the idolatry of the old faith is torn away,
我们将给百姓带来新的希望
we will bring hope to the people.
宣扬正教之时 定是普天同庆
They will cheer in the streets as we bring the true faith.
待公祷书推广于天下
And will do so all the more now the Book of Common Prayer
诵读于各教区 更是举国若狂
will be issued throughout the country, to every parish.
新王爱德华六世万岁
The new Josiah: Edward VI.
The new Josiah: Edward VI!
我等罪民祈求主的垂听
We sinners do beseech thee to hear us, O Lord;
恳请您为普世教会
that it may please thee to rule and govern
指明正道
thy holy Church Universal in the right way.
我等罪民祈求主的垂听
We beseech thee to hear us, O Lord.
你若没冲他发火 恐怕不会这样
All this 'cause you shouted at him.
恳请您...
That it may please thee...
这叫绥靖之计
It's called appeasement.
继续由着他吧
It's always been the strategy.
以明君身份领导我等
...our King and Governor.
我等罪民祈求主的垂听
We beseech thee to hear us, O Lord.
看来这招对他们都很管用
Everyone looks very appeased right now.
以信仰 威慑 仁爱使其臣服
...to rule his heart in thy faith, fear, and love,
恳请您始终...
that it may always have...
开始后悔放主教出狱了
Regretting the bishop's release already?
我等永远追寻您的荣耀与光辉
To ever seek thy honor and glory.
我等罪民祈求主的垂听
We beseech thee to hear us, O Lord.
你到底怎么回事 伙计
What is going on with you, man?
四十年来 你都坚持自我
You spent 40 years resolutely immutable,
如今的你 变化无常 就像...
and now you're as changeable as...
- 像什么 - 你弟弟
- As what? - As your brother.
我等罪民祈求主的垂听
We beseech thee to hear us, O Lord.
你先别担心主教
Don't worry about the bishop.
玛丽
Or Mary.
或是其他人
Or any of that.
教会牧师...
...Ministers of the Church...
她尽管交给我
I have her in hand.
深切领悟 始终谨记
...with true knowledge and understanding
- 您的圣言 - 那他们呢
- of the Word. - What about them?
我等罪民祈求主的垂听
We beseech thee to hear us, O Lord.
他们能怎样
What about them?
通过布道和修行...
And that both by their preaching and living...
玛丽公主不来 我能理解
I can understand why the Princess Mary is not here.
但伊丽莎白公主呢
But the Princess Elizabeth?
我等祈求主的垂听
We beseech thee to hear us O Lord.
我女儿也被他们扔在家里了
And my daughter they've abandoned at home, too, I see.
他们都为某位重病之人高兴
They're all rather jolly for the grievously sick.
所有高贵品质...
...and all the nobility with...
谁病了
Who's sick?
我想是因为凯瑟琳太后怀有身孕
I thought the Lady Catherine was meant to be strained
心力交瘁
by her pregnancy.
才将公主打发走的
Hence the princess' departure from her house.
恐怕没别的原因了
I can't imagine what the other reason could be.
让各民族团结统一...
...to give all nations unity...
大家都在议论
Tongues are wagging.
想要保住舌头 我劝您不要乱说 大人
For the sake or your tongue, I hope not yours, sir.
- 阿门 - 阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
很抱歉留你在这里 简
Sorry we left you behind, Jane.
其实...
It's...
我不希望大家看到我们家的两位姑娘
I didn't want to draw attention to one of our young female wards,
只有一位在场
lest the other one's absence was noted.
本来没必要这样
Though it was pointless.
可在王宫里三次有人问我伊丽莎白在哪里
I was asked where Elizabeth was three times at court.
趁两位心情还好 我们先回去吧
Shall we go back, for you were all smiles there?
看来这家里会演戏的
Seems like you are not the only convincing actor
不只有你
in the house then.
简 你也在伪装吗
Jane, are you acting too?
你也在装出喜欢他的样子吗
Do you pretend also to find him amusing?
夫人 你到底在怀疑什么呢
And what exactly is it that you doubt, my lady?
你
You.
我怀疑你
I doubt you.
那你要我怎样
What would you have me do?
我想让你袖手旁观
I would have you do nothing.
她每周来信 乞求我的宽恕
She writes every week, begging for my forgiveness.
也许我该宽恕她 但...
Maybe I should, but...
我无法回信给她
...I cannot bring myself to reply.
这都是你害的
This is what you have made me.
我不想再关心孩子的事了
I've lost all compassion for a child.
尤其是那个孩子 托马斯
A child, Thomas!
唯一觉得你有点用处的人
The only person that finds you remotely worthwhile
是个十一岁的男孩
is an 11-year-old boy.
他是国王
Well, he is the king.
可他还是个小孩子
An 11-year-old boy.
还有我
And me.
我真是瞎了眼
How much of a fool am I?
别在意她的话
Don't mind Catherine.
我的也别在意
Or me, for that matter.
有时看似难以解决之事
Sometimes things that seem insurmountable,
片刻就能摆平
they're often resolved quickly.
而我们所处的状况皆非永恒
And none of these states that we find ourselves in last forever,
不论欢愉或痛苦
be they pleasure or pain.
源自《希伯来书》第13章 第8节
无论过去现在 耶稣基督始终如一
And yet, Christ is the same yesterday, today, and forever.
心里好受些了吗
Do you take comfort in that?
是的
I do.
亨利那种穷酸废物怎么能
How are you the daughter of that
给你当父亲
dilapidated half-wit Henry?
你就像是鸡窝里飞出的凤凰
It's like watching a goshawk hatch from a goose egg.
我也得走吗
Am I to be sent away too?
还以为你们想让我嫁给国王
I thought you were planning to marry me to the king.
或许不会了 毕竟我对你和凯瑟琳来说...
May not be implemented now that you and Catherine...
现在毫无利用价值
...you may no longer have use of me.
简小姐
Young Jane...
如果你告诉凯瑟琳 自己只是这场游戏中的
if you tell Catherine you think that you have no other use
某颗棋子 你觉得她会怎么想
than as some pawn in a game, how do you think she'd feel?
她每天都告诉我 简怎样妙语连珠
Every day she tells me some clever thing that Jane said
出落得多么窈窕
or how elegant Jane grows.
你真觉得自己没用吗
No use of Jane?
其实不然 你能帮我们很多
No, we got plenty of uses for you yet.
洗碗
Pot washer?
挤奶
Nanny goat milker?
都不行的话 就帮我补袜子
Darn my hose, if all else fails.
你喜欢吗
Would you like that?
记住 你比任何有幸娶你的人
Never forget that you're worth more than any man
都更有价值
who's lucky enough to marry you,
不论是国王 皇帝
be he king or emperor
甚至是园丁约翰尼·古兹威克
or... Johnny Guzzlewick the gardener.
她还要在这里住多久呢
Do you know how much longer she is to remain here?
我希望家仆们
For I would like to one day soon
能早日再吃上热饭热菜
not have to feed our servants scraps from our plates.
是公主
It's princess.
别害怕
Don't lose courage now.
只是见你妹妹
I believe it is only your sister,
就算你畏惧她 她肯定更加畏惧你
and I am sure she's much more afraid of you than you of her.
公主殿下
Princess.
这位是佩德罗先生
This is Sir Pedro.
来自西班牙
He is from Spain.
你喜欢杏子吗
You like apricot?
她还没见过你这样的人
She's never seen one of you before.
你没有去过港口或城镇里吗
You've never been to the ports, the city?
她就没离开过这片地方
She's never been outside the grounds of this place.
你这么害怕 那就出去
Out, if you're so afraid of it.
不然就直面它
Face it.
- 您是指 - 别多想
- "Him." - It.
是她的恐惧 不是你
Her fear. Not you.
她怎么会怕您呢 阁下
Why should she be scared of you, sir?
别管她 阁下
Leave her be, sir.
妹妹
Sister.
知道大家怎么议论你吗
Do you know what they say of you?
- 不知道 - 你在撒谎
- No. - You're already lying to me.
我都不在王宫 怎能知道别人的议论
How can I know what others say when I'm not there?
当然可以 人人能之为之
Of course you can. Everyone can. Everyone does.
抱歉 我不该给你寄那封信
I'm sorry for the letter I sent.
你不说我都忘了
I'd all but forgot it.
你和爱德华的信仰让我左右为难
I was caught between your wishes and Edward's.
可你还是选了他
And you chose his.
所以你才生我的气
So that is why you're angry with me.
不 我生气是因为
No, I'm angry because you have allowed
我意图避免的事 你任由其发生
what I told you would happen to happen.
我知道你自认为比我聪明
I know you think yourself cleverer than me,
可能确实如此
and in truth, you may well be right.
但再聪明的人也需学习 为此
But even the cleverest need learn, and for that,
他们必须听过来人的话
they must listen to those with experience.
妹妹 相信我 我经验丰富
Trust me, sister, I have plenty.
当初真该听你和凯瑟琳的...
I wish I had listened; to you, to Catherine...
那封信里能看出你有多听她的话
Oh, her hand was well-detectable in that letter.
我瞒着她寄出那封信
I sent it without her knowledge.
可你住在她家
You were in her household.
我做的很多事 她都不知道
I did much without her knowledge.
住口
Don't say that.
正因如此 大家才会议论你
That's exactly what they say of you.
无妨
But no matter.
今日我正是为此事而来
That is why I'm here.
你就跟我一同进宫
You will come with me to court,
共同揭穿谎言 大白真相
and we'll show the lies for what they are.
就别委屈自己
No more hiding out here
躲藏在这冷清之地
in the middle of the country as though in disgrace.
是谁让你到这里来的
Whose idea was it for you to come here, of all places?
我是被逼无奈
It was not mine.
- 谁逼你 - 我不知道
- So whose? - I don't know.
不知是何人何时决定的
I don't know who decided it or when,
也不知我何时能离开
or whether I'm even free to leave.
安东尼爵士是要收留我 还是软禁我呢
Is Sir Anthony my host or my jailer?
他听说或知道了什么吗
What was he told? What does he know?
你究竟在说些什么
What on Earth are you talking about?
他能知道什么
What on Earth could he know?
你有事瞒着我
What is there to know?
我不想听
Don't tell me.
我会和盘托出
I'll tell you all.
信奉上帝 切勿多想
Confide in God and God alone.
你能相信的人只有祂
He's the only one you can trust.
那你呢
Not you?
总有人想利用我们
Others will always seek to use us.
你 我 还有弟弟
You, me, and our brother.
他们想看我们自相残杀
They wish us to fight it out to the death
最后追随胜者 坐收渔翁之利
and hope they're standing behind a winner at the end.
那能让你玩火自焚的权力 别交给我
Don't hand me the power to destroy you
交给我 也别指望我不动用
and then ask me not to use it.
我相信你能克制住
I believe you would resist.
你或许不知道 我跟你很像
Maybe I'm more like you than you realize.
我经不住诱惑
I, too, can give in to temptation.
别为难简
Be nice to Jane.
- 她觉得... - 怎么
- She feels as if... - What?
你想占有她吗
Did you try and fuck her as well?
心怀对王位的渴求
You trying to stuff your wad into every young purse
跟王侯千金交欢
with a claim to the throne?
我受够了
I hate this.
真受够了
这就如同古希腊悲剧
It's like watching a Greek tragedy.
开始便知结局
The ending foretold from the start.
但我没想到会来得如此突然
But I didn't think it would come so soon,
就在朝夕之间
not before the milk had soured.
我也没想到你会和她厮混
And I never envisaged it would be with her.
也没想到我会如此受伤
Or that it would hurt this much.
我不会再让你破家散业
I won't let you ruin this.
这样我们都好
For either of us.
这种不幸日子我受够了
I've had enough of this... Of this unhappiness.
是吗 谢谢告知
Have you? That's good to know.
别把我的大度当作投降
Don't make my generosity feel like surrender.
这是我的恩赐
I give you this.
是我饶恕了你
I am giving you forgiveness.
正合我意
I want it.
拜托 凯瑟琳 原谅我吧
Please, God, Catherine, I want it.
你这个小小男爵
Oh, you small man.
听我说完
Don't.
让我看低你
Let me think you small.
总好过让我担心你会怎样
It is better than what I feared you are.
你究竟心性如何
What I fear you are.
你是我的男人
You are my man.
只属于我
My man.
我的
My small...
小小男爵
small man.
得知我来 他有不开心吗
Is he pleased to know that I am here?
他很惊讶 倒也没有不开心
He was surprised, but not unhappily so.
弟弟
Brother.
我们能不要这么剑拔弩张吗
I do not want this. Us, at war.
你 我 还有伊丽莎白 本应团结同心
You, me, and our sister, we are on the same side.
伊丽莎白已经抛弃我们
Elizabeth has abandoned us.
离开切尔西庄园后 她便销声匿迹
Leaves Chelsea and has not been seen since.
- 他们说她身体抱恙 - 但我都见过她了
- They say she's been unwell. - But I've seen her.
她没有故意躲藏 那些谣言...
She's not in some kind of hiding, whatever rumors there...
我告诉过陛下莫听信宫里的流言蜚语
I told Your Grace not to listen to court gossip.
那这些流言起初怎么会传出来呢
Why has any been allowed to start with?
我并非是来谈伊丽莎白的事
I haven't come to speak of Elizabeth.
也无意跟你争执
I haven't come to fight with you.
我们何不痛快玩乐一番
Let's do something that we enjoy.
好吧
Well...
早该如此
we should think of something.
快啄它 快啄它
Go! Come on! Come on!
还愣着作甚 往哪里跑呢
What are you doing? Where are you going?
快上
Come on!
- 快上 - 冲 干翻它
- Come on! - Let's go! Come on!
就这样 击败它
Yes! Just smash him!
啄眼睛 眼睛
Go for the eyes! The eyes!
就这样
Yes!
她日子过得平静
She lives a quiet life.
三餐不误 来往如常
She eats. She talks.
你这消息还真是有用啊
How much do I owe you for this insight?
她为人正直坦诚
She's an honest woman.
有问题的不是她的为人
Her honesty has never been the problem.
而是信仰
It's her faith that is.
还有宣扬异教的执念
And her deep desire to parade it.
主教有试图和她
Has the bishop been attempting
煽动天主教徒谋反吗
to incite any more Catholic rebellions with her?
不是煽动
It was not an incitation.
你在信里可没这么说的
That's not how your letter made it sound.
好
Yes!
他答应过我不再造成
He promised me that he'd cause no more...
你讨厌言而无信的人吗
Do you dislike people not keeping their promises?
你为何要下令排除异教
Why are the churches stripped on your orders?
你留我在玛丽身边
You promised my role with Mary
不是要帮她平息这场宗教纷争吗
was to help end this religious divide.
你只需替我做事
Your role is to be in my employment.
那并非我的职责 大人 是我的决定
That is not a role, sir, but a decision of mine.
你大可另作决定
Well, feel free to make a different one,
但她可不会花钱雇你监视她
but she won't pay you to spy on her.
快 把它眼睛叼出来
Come on! Pluck his eyes out!
你也见过他们拒绝为英苏战争出资的嘴脸
You saw how they resist funding the Scottish wars.
再想想那些金币辉煌的教堂
Those churches are lined with gold.
你想动用教会的香火钱和无辜民众去打仗
You want to fight a war with God's money and other people's blood?
我倒是想亲自浴血杀敌
I'd happily fight it with my own blood.
大不了战死沙场
It's down here that's gonna be the death of me.
你是为上帝 还是你自己而战呢 大人
Do you fight for your god, sir? Or yourself?
我为国王而战
I fight for the king.
那你现在觉得熟对熟错呢
And who do you believe that is right now?
好 太好了
Yes! Yes!
废物阉鸡
Useless capon.
胜利
Win!
有关你家的流言满天飞
There's been enough gossip flapping around your house
都传到我这里了
that it took flight and reached mine.
到底怎么回事 凯瑟琳
What happened, Catherine?
你知道在农村
Do you know what they do
造谣传谣的女人会怎样吗 玛丽
to women in the villages who gossip, Mary?
她们的嘴会被封住
They bind their mouths.
或许我该跟你弟弟 当今的国王提个建议
Perhaps I suggest it to your brother, the king.
你对自己的所作所为很自豪吗
Are you so very proud of your own actions
竟用这副嘴脸对我
that you present this face to me?
你跟你妹妹聊过吗
Have you spoken to your sister?
她怎么说
What did she say?
我不是来替我妹妹传话的
I'm not here to report my sister's words to you.
是想替自己说几句 母后
I'm here to speak my own, Mother.
我真没想到
It was a great surprise to me
你管不好自己的走狗
to learn that you can't muzzle your hound.
更麻烦的不都被你降服了吗
You've muzzled worse, I thought.
想必当时你动过脑筋
But I suppose that's when you used your head.
现在你貌似被什么影响了
Now you seem to be governed by something else.
人心如此 玛丽
It is called a heart, Mary.
看看你现在的愚蠢模样
And what a fool it's made of you.
你经历这么多事
After all that you have been through,
我都看在眼里非常佩服
all that I have seen and admired,
你却选择他
you chose that?
至少我能主动选择 而不是被人挑选
At least I chose him, rather than was chosen.
这是我此生最大的胜利
I will call that victory in this life.
无论你觉得我是软弱 愚蠢
And weak or foolish
还是对我评头论足
or judged as I am by you,
我都会继续生活 守护幸福
I will continue on and be happy.
哪怕付出代价 造成他人的痛苦吗
No matter the cost, in spite of others' misery.
我觉得你卓尔不群
I thought a great many things of you,
但没想到你会如此粗心
but negligence was never one of them.
你这么看的起我吗
You thought many things?
我敬重过你
I respected you.
爱戴过你
And then I loved you.
可我也恨过你
And then I hated you.
来时我也对你心怀恨意
And I came here hating you still.
但现在
But now...
我可怜你
now I pity you.
她刚说了什么
What did she say?
跟我来
Come.
国王跟玛丽已和好
I see Mary's back in favor.
我们接下来该怎么办
How are we meant to keep up?
凯瑟琳和托马斯也还在
Catherine and Thomas still in,
要我把简带出去吗
or should I be getting Jane out of there?
大家对简跟国王的事
I thought everyone's feelings on this Jane scheme
已有明确态度
had been made quite clear.
我看陛下他已经决定
Well, I see the king, it seems, has chosen
与凯瑟琳和托马斯为伍 而非他姐姐
Thomas and Catherine over his own sister.
还有 那个娼妓之女现在何处
Wh... where is the... the sickly whore's daughter?
- 给我住口 格雷 - 你说什么 小子
- Close your mouth, Grey. - What, boy?
你住口 罗伯
Close yours, Rob.
他在蔑称公主殿下
He's talking about the princess!
跟你说话的还是公爵呢 小子
And you're talking to a fucking duke, boy.
我怎么说都行
So I will speak how I like.
她就是娼妓之女
She is the whore's daughter.
我若乐意 还能直接说她是娼妓
If I want, I will call her a whore myself.
小伙子火气挺大啊
Little lad's full of fire!
真想给他破凉水 消消火
Might want to douse his ardent flames.
快走
Out.
你要是打到我 当心你的右手不保
They'd cut off your right hand if you'd done that.
- 可他没有 - 算他走运
- Yes, but he didn't. - Thank God.
想必你的右手还要用段时间
I'll wager you'll be needing yours for some time yet.
我很抱歉 我很抱歉
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
趁他没改主意 赶紧走
Get out before he changes his fucking mind.
我跟你母亲青梅竹马
I knew your mother from childhood.
- 我知道 - 我深爱你母亲
- I know. - I love your mother.
这宫里鲜有人跟其妻是真爱
Not many in court do their wives.
但若是娶英格兰公主为妻...
But Lord, if she'd been a Princess of England...
什么 不 我可没这想法
What? No! I don't... I don't think...
可能你觉得仗着父亲有权有势 凡事有靠山
You may think that because I'm a powerful man, you're protected,
若是在太平盛世 确实如此
and in a steady world, that would be true,
若在乱世 非也
but this world rocks.
你还年轻 觉得为情所伤很浪漫
You're young enough to think heartbreak romantic...
实则不然
it is not.
我从未说过自己喜欢她
I have said no word of feelings for her.
这都是你的臆想 父亲
This is your own fiction, father.
他们说你可能会在这里
They said I might find you here.
你怎么来了
Why have you come?
我觉得有朋友来看你 你会高兴
I thought you might like a visit from a friend.
你不想见我 我可以回去
I can turn back if you wish.
你怎么会觉得我需要朋友陪伴呢
What made you think I was in need of friendship?
或许是我需要朋友陪伴
Maybe it's I who's in need.
不行
I cannot.
我吹不响
还是不行
I cannot.
你的拉丁文和希腊文老师
All your fine tutors of Latin and Greek,
都不教你这个吗
yet no one taught you this?
看来我要学的还有很多
There is much I'm yet to learn, it would seem.
也没人要求你无所不知
Well, no one could expect you to know everything.
要是我能明辨是非就好了
Except the difference between right and wrong.
王宫里人们都在议论我吗
Do they talk about me in court?
他们都在谈萨默赛特公爵和他打的败仗
They are far too busy talking of Lord Somerset and his failing war,
还有斗鸡比赛是否有人暗箱操作
and whether the cockfight was rigged.
实不相瞒 都在关注斗鸡比赛
Mainly the cockfight, though, truth be told.
看来我已被人遗忘
So I'm forgotten.
但肯定有人惦记
Definitely not forgotten.
你若知道我做的事
You wouldn't look at me like that
定会另眼相待
if you knew what I had done.
我相信 不管发生什么 都不能只归咎于你
Whatever's occurred, I doubt all blame can lie with you alone.
是吗
No?
是的
No.
我真是
Shit.
谢谢
Thank you.
您的月事果真是迟来了
I knew you were late.
就知道是您多虑了 殿下
I know you are taken to drama, my lady,
其实你本不必如此担心
but you could have spared it on this one occasion.
不公平
That is unfair.
"Unfair"?
我几乎每周都写信给凯瑟琳
I have written to Catherine near every week.
所以我才总问安东尼爵士
That's why I kept asking Sir Anthony
有无她的音信
if there's been word from her.
我反复恳求她的原谅
I've asked her for forgiveness again and again.
您觉得自己该被原谅吗
You think you deserve it?
你到底想让我看什么
You wish to show me what, exactly?
塑像
The statues.
礼拜堂的金器
The gold from the chantry.
礼拜堂
The chantry?
他们还说我们是"卑鄙无耻的天主教徒"
"Filthy fucking Catholic," They said.
你的正义之举 主都看在眼里
The Lord sees all you do for him.
他不需要主回谢自己受到的屈辱
He does not need the Lord to acknowledge his persecution.
他需要世人的支持
He needs an advocate here on Earth.
- 摄政王答应过... - 莫要相信他
- The Lord Protector swore... - Don't trust the man.
别相信这些人
Don't trust these men.
他们可不像你
They do not act like you do.
他们做事不讲良心
They do not act with conscience.
他会告诉你弟弟这都是为了改革
He tells your brother all of this is in the name of reform,
实则抢夺我们的财富 中饱私囊
but he robs from us to line his own pockets
以资助一场罪恶的战争
and fund a godless war.
这场游戏中 只有你会遵守规则
You are the only player in this game worrying about the rules.
我怎配有这孩子
She's more than I deserve.
这是上帝的决定
That's for God to decide.
我怕自己罪孽深重
I fear I'm too much of a sinner
会辜负上帝的好意
to give myself up to His will completely.
也许是你人很好却不自知
Maybe you're a better man than you think.
你要进来吗
You coming in?
我来
Hey.
之前的事
No more.
不会再有了
Of before.
我保证
I promise.
我不想要你的承诺
I don't want your promise.
不需要
I don't need it.
也许大家都不理解我怎么会嫁给你
Perhaps no one will understand my marriage to you.
我也不理解
I certainly don't.
我跟说的话 你会回应
But I speak to you, and you answer.
我让你做什么
I ask you to do things.
有时你会照做 有时不会
Sometimes you do, sometimes you don't...
但你至少会听
but you do at least listen.
我的想法也好 决定也好
To my thoughts, to my decisions.
- 把你当作你男人看待 - 是的
- As if you were a man. - Indeed.
你把我看作活生生的人
As if I were a person.
我看着孩子
I look at mine,
真想捏捏他们的小脸蛋
and I-I want to squeeze their little faces!
但有时候
Other times,
这些小丫头片子就是欠收拾
the troublesome wenches are begging for a slap.
即便如此 我动手也是出于爱
But even then, even then, it is with love.
- 打是亲 - 打是亲
- With love! - With love!
骂是爱
With love!
托马斯 有时候还是要唱黑脸
But don't be afraid to be a bastard to them, Thomas.
对 都是出于爱
Yes. With love.
- 严父出孝子 - 没错
- Admonishing. - Admonishing.
说得好
Good advice.
- 爵士大人 - 简
- Sir? - Jane.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas?
你会吵醒孩子的
You're gonna wake the babe.
托马斯爵士 拜托你快过去
Sir Thomas. My lord. My lord, please.
我正要去看她呢
I'm just gonna go look at her.
等等 托马斯爵士
Wait, Sir Thomas...
爵士大人
Sir.
抱歉 我们尽力了
I'm sorry. I'm so sorry.
凯瑟琳
Catherine?
孩子别哭
Hush now, my child.
摄政王
My lord.
你终于来了 我等你很久了
Finally, sir. You kept me waiting.
我收到一条消息
I received a message.
我收到的消息更为要紧
Your messages are not as important as mine.
看看这个 摄政王
I received this, Lord Protector.
苏格兰玛丽女王和法国王储的
An invitation to the wedding of Mary Queen of Scots
婚礼请柬
and the Dauphin of France.
他们竟然敢邀请我
They send me this!
她本应该作我妻子 可战争仍未结束
She was meant to be my wife, and the war still rages!
你何时才能不再让我和这个国家
When will the humiliation you have put me
继续蒙羞
and this country through end?
他们不该寄给你的
They... They should not have sent this.
你要说的也是这消息吗
And that's all you have to say?
不 是凯瑟琳·帕尔崩逝了
No. Catherine Parr is dead.
死于产褥热
Childbed fever.
具体死因不详
I'm not sure.
命数如此
God's will.
她的遗产将归还国王
Her possessions are to be returned to the crown.
并且国王决定将切尔西庄园
And so the crown has decided Chelsea Place is to go to you,
连同其他财物都归你所有
along with a great many other things.
你既已成年 这些财产就没人能替你接受
You are of age, and there's no one left to claim you.
现在你富有了
You are rich.
老实说 全国上下
In fact, the only woman in the country
只有你姐姐比你有钱有势
with more wealth and influence is your sister.
等你准备好 我就护送你
I am to escort you as soon as you are ready
乔迁新居
to take up residence.
- 还有谁要走 - 只有你自己
- With whom? - With yourself.
你会有许多参事与谏臣
You will have advisors and counselors aplenty.
但都是无用的食客罢了
Useless pissants to a man.
相信你能承担重任 自主决定
But I'm sure you're quite capable of making your own decisions.
亨利
Henry!
你觉得她还能留下来吗
You didn't think she could stay, did you?
上车
In the carriage.
他没对你...
He didn't...
做什么吧
with you?
你们没有...
There was no...
那就好
Good.
好
起驾
On!
驾 驾
Come on! Come on.
托马斯 你搬来我家住吧
You're to come and stay with me, Thomas.
别再推诿了 爵士
Try not to argue, sir.
木已成舟
It won't change anything.
妻子魂归西天 只留个女儿给我
Not a boy and a dead wife.
如今我一败涂地
I've thoroughly failed this assignment.
你肯定暗自狂喜
You must be immensely pleased.
说什么傻话
Don't be stupid.
我坐在楼下
I sat downstairs, and...
等待命运的安排 但是
I waited for life, but...
我总会想起她离世的画面
...my mind, it wandered to her death.
也许
Maybe...
是我自作自受
maybe I brought it into being.
我家孩子出生时
When our children were born,
我也略感
I believe I did that.
愧疚
A little.
心中有数 谨防万一
Ready oneself, in case.
这不怪你
I think it natural.
凯瑟琳走得很安详
Catherine seemed well.
没错
Yes.
就像我们的简
As our sister did.
没错
Yeah.
简和她儿子
There were but 12 days in this world
只在这世上共度了十二天
where there was both our sister and her son in it.
看着现在的爱德华
I look at Edward now,
我虽知道自己是他舅父
and though I know I'm his uncle,
但我却未想起
I... I clear forget that...
他是简的儿子
that she bore a son at all.
有时爱德华跟简很像
No, I see her in the king sometimes.
这让我很惊讶 但确实如此
It takes me quite by surprise, but I do.
时常这样觉得
From time to time.
我觉得他只是爱德华
I just see the boy as he is.
有时觉得他那嘴脸很像亨利·都铎
Or I see Henry fucking Tudor.
实在可怕
That is uncanny.
老混蛋起死回生
The old cunt back from the dead,
附身于爱德华 气得跺脚
possessing him to stamp his feet.
托马斯
Thomas.
上帝惩戒我时
No, but as God persecutes me,
我认为他最狠的招
I think his greatest trick...
就是让你孤苦伶仃
is that he leaves you still well alone.
或许每当我被抛弃时 就会这么觉得
Perhaps it's so that I can always see when I'm denied.
上帝不会戏弄世人
God doesn't play tricks.
那是你
On you.
你在这世上闯荡时 就是应天顺民
For the world, it parts and it bows
而我却命途多舛 饱经忧患
as you move through it, while I struggle uphill,
等我好不容易取得成就
and as soon as I get anywhere, in God steps
上帝又害得我功败垂成
just to push me back down again.
你笑什么
What amuses you so, sir?
笑我丧妻
My dead wife?
笑我女儿丧母
My motherless child?
还是我的悲惨人生
Or my cursed life?
不 我没嘲笑你
No, I'm... I'm not amused.
只是惊异于你对世事的看法
I'm just... I'm a little in wonder at how you see things.
托马斯 你对世界的看法
Your view out onto the world, Thomas,
跟其他人都略有不同
is a little different from the one that the rest of us have.
所以你觉得遭受折磨的不只是我
So you think I'm not uniquely tortured.
先是我姐姐
First our sister,
再是我妻子
then my wife,
所有的美好都被...
taken just as everything seemed...
离我而去
everything seemed well.
简亲眼看到她儿子 未来的国王
Our sister saw her son, the future king,
由我们带到教堂 在万众敬仰中
carried by us ahead of the whole court
接受洗礼
to his christening.
那不是她期盼已久的日子吗
Would she not have wanted that day?
凯瑟琳也抱过自家女儿
Catherine held her daughter,
既无痛苦 也不惊慌
not in panic or in pain.
而是亲吻怀中的孩子
She held and kissed her baby
感念平安
thinking that both were safe.
上帝祝福她们母女
God stayed his hand to bless them
赐予她们分离前的美好时光
by gifting them those days.
难道你会舍弃这些美好
You wouldn't wish them away
以减轻自身的悲痛吗
because it would ease your suffering.
我会
I would.
我不喜欢悲痛
I do not like suffering.
各位 放好行李吧
Ladies, let's unpack.
仪式即将开始
We're about to start.
刚才没看见你
Didn't know where you'd gone.
为凯瑟琳·帕尔做弥撒吗
A mass for Catherine Parr?
她曾是我朋友
She was my friend once.
你为敌人祈祷
You pray for your enemies?
为所有人
For all.
那也为我祈祷吧
Pray for me, then.
何出此言
Sir?
原本我是受摄政王之命来监视你
The Lord Protector sent me to spy on you.
用小恩小惠来稳住你
Tempting you with morsels to keep you quiet
以便他掌控大局
whilst he runs wild.
他想要控制你和你弟弟
He wants power over you and your brother.
为何现在告诉我
Why are you telling me this now,
你出卖我
that you have betrayed me?
我此生都在渴望看到
I've spent my whole life waiting for men
人能彰显自己的尊严
to prove themselves honorable.
可却发现 再正直虔敬的人
But no matter how decent or pious,
都会屈服于金钱
they all had their price.
所以我觉得自己作雇佣兵没什么不好
It's how I.. I justified becoming a mercenary.
我犯不着贵人贱己
Because I was no worse than any other man.
甚至很多人不如我 至少我诚实
Better, in fact, because I, at least, was honest.
遇到您之后
And then I met you.
我开始觉得 也许...
And I'm beginning to see that perhaps I...
我错了
I was wrong.
恕我冒昧 如今您已回到此地
I suppose you're in a hurry to return to court
想必会急着回宫觐见陛下吧
now that you're finally back here.
我不想进宫
I have no desire to be at court.
那您有何想法 公主殿下
Then what do you want, Lady Elizabeth?
我不知道
I don't know.
您肯定有想法 女人都这样
Of course you do. All women do.
只是您更善于掩饰
You're just trained to disguise it.
男人的野心受人欣赏 女人的野心受人嘲弄
Ambition is much-admired in men but derided in women.
您究竟有何打算
But what do you want?
您在人前自然
It will indeed serve you
需要收敛锋芒
to hide what you want from others,
但对自己要坦诚
but do not keep it from yourself.
先王根本不在乎谣言
Your father didn't give a fuck about rumors,
您若在乎 就该出手辟谣
but if you do, they should be stopped.
摄政王也该这么做
The Lord Protector should have done so.
摄政王要是听到些风言风语
If they have reached the Lord Protector,
恐怕他会信以为真
I doubt he has believed them,
其他人若也信 必然引起风波
or any have, else there would have been consequence.
风波已兴
There was.
这跟我无关 公主殿下 请相信我
I am no consequence, Princess, believe me.
可谣言无论多离谱
But still people chatter.
人们依旧议论纷纷
And however false,
我怎么能影响别人对我的看法呢
how can I control what others say of me?
您能做到
Oh, you can.
殿下 您绝对可以
Lord, of course you fucking can.
您这无异于州官放火 可要想清楚
You know how much this will stoke the fires at court.
哪又如何
Let them burn.
公主殿下
Princess.
达德利勋爵
Lord Dudley.
烦请通报陛下 我有话想跟他说
Let my brother know I am here and would like an audience.
陛下
Your Majesty.
此番前来 是想向您认罪
I come before you with a confession.
我曾少不更事 自私自利
I have been selfish and naive,
甚至误解陛下
and I have wronged you.
姐姐 何出此言呢
Why say you this, sister?
我没有尽到自身责任
I've neglected my duties.
凯瑟琳太后怀孕后
Our Lady Catherine was blessed with child,
为让她顺利分娩 我搬去切森特
so I took myself to Cheshunt for her confinement
不久便身体抱恙
and was then myself taken ill.
生病不是借口
Illness is no excuse.
责任重于泰山
Duty is more important.
包括对上帝 对您的责任
Duty to God and duty to you.
我是您的忠臣
I am your servant.
我知道有人妄加揣测我销声匿迹的原因
I know some have speculated on the reasons for my absence.
今日 我在此声明 勿要再生谣言
I am here to show that there is no need.
我将自己献给您 陛下
And I offer myself to you, brother.
我属于您
I am yours,
别无他人
and yours alone.
姐姐请起
Stand, sister.
本王原谅你的无故离开
The crown forgives your absence
欢迎回来
and welcomes your return.
起歌奏乐
Let us have music.
好生庆祝此事
Let us celebrate this.
终于平反昭雪
A fine rehabilitation.
我可不想回归当初
That would be to return as I once was.
曾经的无知少女
That girl was a fool.
已经死了
That girl is dead.
好了吗
Ready?
嫁给我
Marry me.
奏乐
Play.
■
更多精彩 请登录深影论坛 shinybbs.vip
深影字幕组微博 weibo.com/syfansub
■
关注深影字幕组
微信公众号，更
多影视资讯，等
你来发现